Leroy Ireland research material on George Inness
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Leroy Ireland research material on George Inness
1916-2007, bulk 1960-1971
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Ireland, Leroy
2.0 linear feet
Art dealer Leroy Ireland's research material on George Inness measures 2.0 linear feet and dates from 1916 to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1960 to 1971. The collection documents Ireland's research for his book The Works of George Inness: An Illustrated Catalogue Raisonne through correspondence, research files, and photographs of artwork.
Provenance
Two letters and photographs of artwork were donated in 1963-1964 by Ireland; the remainder of the papers were donated in 1993 by Mrs. Leory Ireland via executor Irene Chapellier Little, and in 2010 by the Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, Philadelphia, Penn. who received the collection from John Frisk, a friend of Ireland.
Separated Material
In 1975, additional Leroy Ireland research material regarding George Inness was lent by Chapellier Galleries in New York City who had acquired the material from Ireland's estate; this material is available on microfilm reels 992-996 and include an extensive photograph file of Inness paintings; correspondence; notes on and descriptions of paintings; sales records of Inness's works; ownership records of Inness paintings; information about questionable attributions; exhibition catalogs and miscellany.
Twelve scrapbooks compiled by Ireland were lent by Archer Huntington Art Gallery of the University of Texas at Austin in 1983 and are currently located at the Fine Arts Library, University of Texas at Austin. These scrapbook contain circa 3,000 photographs of Inness paintings and are available on reels 2824-2825. Materials loaned for microfilming are not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Leroy Ireland (1889-1970) was an art dealer and painter in New York and Philadelphia. Ireland is best know for his research on the works of landscape painter George Inness (1825-1894), culminating in a catalogue raisonne of his work.
Ireland began his career as a painter, studying with Thomas Eakins at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts and exhibiting in many shows during the 1920s. He moved to New York and became an art dealer and appraiser. During that time he also studied and became an expert in the work of George Inness, specializing in the authentication of works held by galleries, museums, and private collectors. After nearly 30 years of research, his book The Works of George Inness: An Illustrated Catalogue Raisonne was published by the University of Texas Press in 1965.
Scope and Content Note
Art dealer Leroy Ireland's research material on George Inness measures 2.0 linear feet and dates from 1916 to 2007, with the bulk of the material dating from 1960 to 1971. The collection documents Ireland's research for his book The Works of George Inness: An Illustrated Catalogue Raisonne through correspondence, research files, and photographs of artwork.
Leroy Ireland's correspondence is with museums, galleries, private collectors, universities, and others regarding paintings by George Inness and works attributed to him. The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1960 to 1969 during the period that Ireland was working on the catalogue raisonne. Scattered research files include a notebook, notes, and lists of works; photographs, letters, and documents regarding Inness which were received by Mrs. Ireland after Leroy Ireland's death; exhibition catalogs and other printed material. Also found are two copies of letters written by Inness. Photographs depict paintings by George Inness, paintings attributed to Inness but determined to be fakes, and paintings by other artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 3 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1916-2007 (Box 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 2: Research Files Regarding George Inness, 1925-1973 (Box 2; 7 folders)
Series 3: Photographs, circa 1919-1972 (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Inness, George, 1825-1894
Subjects-Topical:
Landscape painting; Painting, Modern--19th century; Painters; Art dealers--Pennsylvania; Art historians--Pennsylvania; Landscape painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1916-2007, Series 1:; (Box 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
  Found here is Leroy Ireland's correspondence with museums, galleries, private collectors, universities, and others regarding paintings by George Inness and works attributed to him. The bulk of the correspondence dates from 1960 to 1969 during the period that Ireland was working on the Inness catalogue raisonne, but earlier related correspondence is included. Also included is correspondence addressed to Mrs. Leroy Ireland on the same subject and letters from art historian Michael Quick to John Frisk regarding Ireland's research files.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - Adams, Davidson & Company (Judith Webster), 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Addison Gallery of American Art, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ainslie Galleries, 1917, 1933-1942 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albany Institute of History and Art, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Albright-Knox Art Gallery, 1951, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Masters Gallery, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Amherst College, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Antiques Magazine, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Arkell Hall (Canajoharie Library and Art Gallery), 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Art Museum of the New Britain Institute, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Art Institute of Chicago, 1949, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Auslew Gallery, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - A, Miscellaneous, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Babcock Galleries, 1957-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ball State Teachers College, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Baylor University, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Berry-Hill Galleries, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Best, Mrs. Edward J., 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Birmingham Museum of Art, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bowdoin College Museum of Art, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brooklyn Museum, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Butler Institute of American Art, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - B, Miscellaneous, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Campanile Galleries, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Castano Galleries, 1944, 1955-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Chapellier Galleries, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cikovsky, Nicolai, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cincinnati Art Museum, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cleveland Museum of Art, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Closuit, Ernest, 1948-1965 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cooper Union, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Currier Gallery of Art, 1955, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - C, Miscellaneous, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - David B. Findlay Galleries, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Davis Galleries, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Detroit Institute of Arts, 1944, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Dibble, Alice, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Doll & Richards, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - D, Miscellaneous, 1957-1969 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Elgin Academy, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Ellsworth, Mary, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - E, Miscellaneous, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Fogg Art Museum, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Frankel, Perry, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Fruhauf, Bedrich, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - F, Miscellaneou, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Garey Galleries, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - George Walter Vincent Smith Art Museum, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Goldfield, Edward, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Gore, F. Fitzgerald, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Grand Central Art Galleries, 1950-1963 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Grand Rapids Art Gallery, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Guild Hall, East Hampton, NY, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - G, Miscellaneous, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Hackley Art Gallery, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Hanzel Galleries, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Harmsen, William, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Hirschl & Adler, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - H, Miscellaneous, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - James Graham and Sons, 1963-1969 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Jelks, Vivian, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Joe and Emily Lowe Art Gallery (Univ. of Miami), 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Joslyn Art Museum, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - J, Miscellaneous, 1949, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Kennedy Galleries, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Keyser, Mrs. Carl Schurz, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Kohler, Mel, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - K, Miscellaneous, 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Lake View Gallery, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Landesman, Fred, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Lane Press, Inc., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Libby, Scott, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Liddell, Frank A. Jr., 1960-1967 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - L, Miscellaneous, 1953, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - M. Knoedler & Co., 1948, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - MacKay, Mrs. J. W., 1969 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Maxwell Galleries, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - McErlean, Charles, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - McIntyre, Robert (Macbeth Gallery), 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Midtown Galleries, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Milch Galleries, 1946-1966 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Mills, Edwin J., 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Mint Museum of Art, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Montclair Art Museum, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Mullin, Ralph, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, 1953, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - M, Miscellaneous, 1941, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - National Gallery of Art, Washington, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - National Gallery of Canada, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Newark Museum, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Norfolk Museum, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - North Carolina Museum of Art, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Northwestern University, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - N-O, Miscellaneous, 1916, 1960-1970 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Paine Art Center and Arboretum, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Parke-Bernet Galleries, 1957-1970 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Pasadena Art Museum, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Phillips Gallery, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Pioneer Museum & Haggin Galleries, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Princeton University, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1951, 1960-1968 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Quick, Micheal, 1991, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - R. W. Norton Art Gallery, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Randolph Macon Women's College, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rembrandt Art Gallery, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rhode Island School of Design, 1952, 1962, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Robert S. Sloan Gallery, 1963-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Roman, Herbert, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - R, Miscellaneous, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Safron, Joe, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Santa Barbara Museum of Art, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Schweitzer, M. R., 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Shipley, Carl, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Southwestern University, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Spanierman, Ira, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Stockwell, A. H., 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - S, Miscellaneous, 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tavoliero, Guy, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - T, Miscellaneous, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Union League Club, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - University of Florida, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - University of Georgia (Georgia Museum of Art), 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - University of Illinois, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - University of Kansas Museum of Art, 1953-1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - University of Minnesota, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - University of Nebraska, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - University of Texas, University Art Museum, circa 1961-1970, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - University of Texas Press, circa 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - U, Miscellaneous, 1960-1969 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Van Dellen, Theodore, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Vassar College, 1952, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Verne, Otto, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Vose Galleries, 1943-1969, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
  - V, Miscellaneous, circa 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Wadsworth Atheneum, 1960, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Walters Art Gallery, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Washington County Museum of Fine Arts, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - William Rockhill Nelson Gallery of Art, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Williams College, Lawrence Art Museum, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Witte Memorial Museum, 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - W, Miscellaneous, 1941, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Yale University Art Gallery, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Y-Z, Miscellaneous, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Research Files Regarding George Inness, 1925-1973, Series 2:; (Box 2; 7 folders)
  This series contains scattered research files regarding George Inness. Included are a notebook containing Ireland's original listing of works by Inness; additional notes and lists of works; and photographs, letters, and documents regarding Inness which were received by Mrs. Ireland after Leroy Ireland's death. Also found are two copies of letters from Inness, one to a Mr. Berch ?, Sept. 1879, and one to Edward D. Adams, Jan. 11, 1888, thanking him for payment for his painting "Sunset," purchased for Adams by Thomas Clarke (a photograph of the painting is included). Additional material includes Inness exhibition catalogs, a published biographical summary, and an printed advertisement for Ireland's catalogue raisonne.
  - Documents received by Mrs. Ireland after Leroy Ireland's Death, 1969-1973, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
  - George Inness Exhibiton Catalogs, 1925-1966 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Letters Written by George Inness (Copies), circa 1963- 1964 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Notebook, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Notes and Lists, circa 1960-1970s (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Printed Material, 1936, circa 1966 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Photographs, circa 1919-1972, Series 3:; (Box 2; 0.3 linear feet)
  Photographs are of paintings by George Inness, paintings attributed to Inness but determined to be fakes, and paintings by other artists. All photographs are annotated.
  - Photographs of Artwork by George Inness, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Photographs of George Inness "Fakes", circa 1963-1972, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 53-54)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Others (Box 2)
    - Sir William Beechey, 1927-1936 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Giovanni Bellini; Margaret Carpenter; Francois Clouet, circa 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - John S. Copley, circa 1930-1965 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Francis Cotes; Richard Cosway; Lucas Cranach, circa 1929-1935 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Marie Dieterle; Gainsborough Dupont; Thomas Gainsborough, 1928-1940 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - John W. Gordon; Frans Hals; George H. Harlow, 1926-1939 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - John Hoppner; Adrien Isenbrandt, 1926-1952 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Angelica Kauffmann; Thomas Lawrence, circa 1919-1932 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Corneille de Lyon; Giovanni Moroni; Jean Nattier; Peter Neefs, 1923-1956 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - William Owen; Rev. M. W. Peters; Thomas Phillips, circa 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Maurice Prendergast; Sir Henry Raeburn, 1926-1967 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Del Garbo Raffaellino; Allan Ramsay; Sir Joshua Reynolds, 1924-1935 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - George Romney; Peter Paul Rubens; Sir Martin A. Shee, circa 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - John R. Smith; Gilbert Stuart; Jacopo Tintoretto, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - J. M. W. Turner; Anthony van Dyck; Frederick Watts; John Zoffany, circa 1926-1932 (Box 2, Folder 69)